Hi I'm Angela Guenette
你好 我是Angela Guenette
and I'm going to talk about some of the work I did on the film Sintel
接下来我来给大家讲讲我在Sintel上所做的工作
These are the same techniques I've used working in Maya, Softimage XSI
我曾经使用Maya和XSI制作过片子
On productions such as the featured film "Everyone's Hero"
比如故事片《棒球小英雄》
and the DVD movie "Barbie as Rapunzel"
DVD影片《芭比娃娃之长发公主》
and the television "Spider-man: The New Animated Series"
还有动画版《蜘蛛侠》
As I demonstrate
我可以证明
these techniques work really well in blender
在Blender中也可以做得不比它们(Maya,XSI)差
In this first part
首先呢
we are going to look at how I organize facial topology specifically for animation use
我先教大家怎么做角色动画人物的脸部
the vertical span in the center of the face separates the left and right side
这条中垂线把面部分为左右两部分
for the eye area
眼球周围
the vertical span ran across the pupil
中垂线跨越了瞳孔
matching the up eyelid center to the bottom eyelid center
正好与上眼皮和下眼皮中心重合
as the same center line also divides the inner eyebrow and the outer eyebrow
这条线也和眉毛的中心重合
for the other corners of the mouth
对于嘴角落来说
we have three holes onto spans
有3条重要的线
the center span
中间线
which divides upper and lower portion
它把这里分为上下两部分
and two supporting span on either side
另外两条辅助线分别在两边
the eye area is also organized in same way as the mouth
眼角部分的结构和嘴角是一样的
with center span and two supporting spans on either side
都是一条中间线以及两条辅助线
the eyebrow location is clearly defined by two parallel spans
两条平行线清楚的描绘了眉毛的位置
encircling the eye area is a mask like continued span
包围在眼睛周围线条就像一个面具
nose and mouth area are also contained together
嘴和鼻子的线条是相连的
this defined the upper and lower portion of the face
这些线条描绘了面部的上下两部分
using extrude select
使用快速选取
you can see how the lip line is defined by two parallel loops
你可以看到唇线是被平行的环形线所描绘的
for the luff line
关于环形线
we have a central loop with two supporting loops
都是由一个中心环和两个辅助环组成
and the crease of eyelids are also defined in this way
眼睛的皱纹就是这样描绘的
taking a closer look in 3 quarter of view
我们近点儿看
you can see how the three parallel spans meet at the top, middle and bottom edge of nostril
你就能看到三条环形线交汇于鼻翼旁边
the middle span is used to create the crease
中心线是用来制造褶皱
also in wireframe they should look like luff lines
当然线框要做成环形线的样子
additional spans are used to continue the smooth transition inside the mouth and eye-socks
嘴和眼睛周围其它的线条是用来处理平滑过渡的
here I'm using Ctrl and Numpad Plus key to increase my selection
这里我使用[Ctrl+小键盘+号]来提高选择面积
building your geometry like this with continued edge loops made it very easy to select areas of the face when working with your model
在做面部的时候 多使用环形线的话 可以在选择线的时候得到很多便利
here you can see closely how the top lip and bottom lip mirror each other
这里你可以看到 上嘴唇和下嘴唇的线条是相对应的
also
还有
vertical spans from top to bottom lineup
垂直区域也是相对应的
taking a closer look at the eyelids
我们来观察一下眼睛
you can see how the topology is organized in the same way as the mouth
你可以看到这里和嘴的结构基本一样
the outer edge of the eyelids are also defined by two spans
眼皮是由两条线组成的
which are highlighted here in grey color
就是这个灰色的区域
the next span in fits the eyeball creating a shelf
靠里面的那条线
or the thickness of the eyelid
描绘了眼皮的厚度
adding a two-line geometry is a very effective way to add life to the eyes
加上这两条线就像画龙点睛一样给了眼活生生的感觉
to make this
为了做这些
I simply duplicate the eyelid shelf and then reshaped it
我只是简单的复制了眼皮的面 并且做了一些非常简单的改进
creating a slide curve that will catch the light better
创建一个光滑的曲线这样就能很好的捕光
the cornea is the glossy transparent part increasing the eye
眼角膜是眼睛里一个光滑透明的部分
when shaping the eyelids I leave the cornea in solid display
当塑造眼皮的时候 我让角膜以[Solid]的方式显示
which ensures the proper fit without gaps or intersection
这是为了保证不会制造穿帮
OK
很好
let's hide the proxy here to display the scalp
让我们先把头发隐藏起来 让头部显示出来
in the property panel under materials
在材质菜单下的属性面板中
you can see how I've divided aparts of the topology with individual material colors
你将看到我是如何使用个人定制的颜色将这些结构上色的
the grey topology material clearly displays placement for the hair and eyebrows
灰色清楚的显示了头发和眉毛位置
it also helps to define where the scalp will end and the forehead begin
当然 这也间接描绘了 哪里是头顶部和额头的边界
now let's select the "topology_lashline" material
现在 让我们选中"topology_lashline"材质
this defines where the eyelashes will be
这个材质就是睫毛
after having these three areas clearly marked
在这三部分标记上之后
I simply duplicate the mesh to create these particle emitter meshes
我简单的复制了这些线条去创建'particle emitter meshes'(这3个词不会翻译)
to conclude the section on facial topology
在这个章节的最后
let's bring in the shaman and dragon baby beside Sintel to compare
让我们把男巫 小傻龙 以及Sintel大小姐比较一下
as you can see here
你可以看到
although they each have their own tailor-made topology
尽管他们都有自己独特的面部结构
from old man to young girl to creature
从老人到御姐再到禽兽
the inner structure closely follows the same principles
总体的结构大致还是一样的
which pretty much ends up in pre-assembling the muscles of the face
几乎都是符合面部肌肉的分布的
the blend files that I've included in the tutorials package have seen "Simplify" enabled
我在教程里的[*.blend]文件都已经把[Simplify]属性激活
to view models in higher resolution
为了观察更高分辨率的模型
just raise the value for the subdivision level
仅仅增加细分级别就可以了
or disable "Simplify"
或者直接关闭[Simplify]也是可以的